Finding Aid for Michigamua Records 1902-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigamua Records 1902-1992
Michigamua.
6 oversize folders
1 oversize boxes
4.1 linear feet
University of Michigan senior honors society with initiation rites, costumes and other rituals based on supposed Native Amerincan traditions; records include chronological "tribe" files, minutes of meetings, topical files, visual materials, and printed materials.
87248; Bimu F42 2; UBImul F42
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated in a number of accessions from various sources, the majority from Michigamua (Donor No. 8149 ) in 1993.
The record group is open for research.
Michigamua is one of the best-known senior honor societies for men at the University of Michigan and is dedicated to bringing together outstanding upperclassmen to foster a loyalty to the university and to promote good class fellowship (Box 3, Folder: Topical Files, History and Traditions, General; Document: "The Great Charter of the Tribe of Michigamua"). Michigamua was created in Spring 1901 by a group of students belonging to the Class of 1902. These students, all of whom attended the Literary College (now the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts) and met nightly to study together, had formed The Hot Air Club in Fall 1900. This club was expanded to include students from other units in Spring 1901 and, after much research into Native American lore, the name of the club was changed to Michigamua. Selection for membership was based upon loyalty to the university and to their class, as well as prominence in an activity that brought credit to both (William F. Temple, The Founding of Michigamua, p. 16). Members often held positions of note in student government or on student publications, or excelled in athletics or scholastic endeavors. With the Tribe of 1903, it was decided to limit the number of active members, or "Fighting Braves," to no more than twenty-five men.
A student is invited to join Michigamua in the winter term of his junior year by means of a tradition of "tapping" which occurs late at night. The student then undergoes the rites of initiation on "Rope Day." All members are assigned a nickname, such as Babbling Brook, intended to reflect a characteristic, trait, or activity of a brave. The active tribe meets on a regular basis in the "Wigwam," located in a tower of the Michigan Union. Alumni of Michigamua are referred to as "Old Braves" and remain active by means of the Old Braves Council which advises the active tribe on various matters. Occasionally a prominent member of the faculty or administration may be invited to join Michigamua as an honorary member or "Honorary Sachem."
The records of Michigamua consist of four linear feet and five outsize folders and span the years from its creation in 1902 to the present. They document the activities of past Michigamua tribes, the role of the Old Braves within the society, and the development of Michigamua traditions. The records are divided into five series: Chronological Tribe Files, Meeting Minutes, Topical Files, Visual Materials, and Printed Materials.
Subjects:
Michigamua.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Michigamua.; Students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Totem poles.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Genre/Form:
College publications.; Directories.; Histories.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Programs.; Student publications.
Publication Titles
Tower talk
- Chronological Tribe Files
  The Chronological Tribe Files (.8 linear feet) span the years 1908 to 1992 and contain materials generated and received by a tribe during their active year. Such materials include membership lists, correspondence with Old Braves and the Old Braves Council, initiation plans, proposals for Honorary Sachems, and annual financial reports.
  The correspondence with Old Braves is especially interesting both for its historical anecdotes, as well as for its expressions of concern about and support for various campus issues. Historical anecdotes and references are scattered throughout the Chronological Tribe Files. For example, the folder "Tribe of 1955" contains an historical account of the Michigamua pin and ring. Acquisition of the totem pole is documented in the folder "Tribe of 1957." A history of Rope Day can be found in the folder "Tribe of 1958."
  Among the campus issues examined in the correspondence are: plans for a cooperative bookstore in the Michigan Union in the "Tribe of 1949" folder; the ban on student automobiles in the "Tribe of 1953" folder; women cheerleaders in the "Tribe of 1958" folder; and student unrest in Tribe folders of the late 1960s and early 1970s. Also, the folder "Tribe of 1973" contains documentation of the complaint filed with the Michigan Civil Rights Commission against Michigamua for its portrayal of Native American traditions. The folder "Tribe of 1977" contains documentation of the complaints brought against Michigamua for alleged violations of Title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 and of Title IX of the Education Amendments Act of 1972 relating to Michigamua's exclusion of women.
  - Tribe of 1908 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1916 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1918 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1922, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Tribes of 1923 and 1924 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1925 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1928 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1929 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1930 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1931 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1932 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1933 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1935 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1936 (Box 1)
  - Tribes of 1938 and 1939 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1940 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1941 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1942 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1943 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1944 (Box 1)
  - Tribes of 1945 and 1946 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1947 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1948 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1949 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1950 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1951 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1952 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1953 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1954 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1955 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1956 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1957 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1958 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1959 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1960 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1961 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1962 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1963 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1964 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1965 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1966 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1967 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1968 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1969 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1970 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1971 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1972 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1973 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1974 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1975 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1976 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1977 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1978 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1980 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1981 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1982 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1983 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1984 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1985 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1986 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1987 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1988 (Box 1)
  - Tribe of 1989 (Box 1)
  - Pride of 1991 (Box 1)
  - Pride of 1992 (Box 1)
- Meeting Minutes
  The Meeting Minutes (1.2 linear feet) are arranged chronologically by academic year and date from 1906/07 to 1986/87. Except for a ten-year gap from 1975/76 through 1984/85, the meeting minutes are fairly complete. They are mostly handwritten and seem to be primarily administrative in content. It should be noted that Michigamua has its own method of recording dates: days are referred to as "Sleeps," months are "Moons," and years are "Hunts." Originally, the months were referred to numerically, i.e., First Moon, Second Moon, etc; however, by 1907, Michigamua had substituted new names for each of the months. January, for example, is the Moon of New Hearts. A list of the Moons can be found at the beginning of the 1915/16 Meeting Minutes.
  - 1906/1907 (Box 1)
  - 1907/1908 (Box 1)
  - 1908/1909 (Box 1)
  - 1909/1910 (Box 2)
  - 1912/1913 (Box 2)
  - 1914/1915 (Box 2)
  - 1915/1916-1923/1924 (bound volume) (Box 2)
  - 1924/1925-1932/1933 (bound volume) (Box 2)
  - 1934/1935 (Box 2)
  - 1936/1937 (Box 2)
  - 1937/1938 (Box 2)
  - 1938/1939 (Box 2)
  - 1939/1940 (Box 2)
  - 1940/1941 (Box 2)
  - 1942/1943 (Box 2)
  - 1943/1944 (Box 2)
  - 1946/1947 (Box 2)
  - 1947/1948 (Box 2)
  - 1948/1949 (Box 2)
  - 1949/1950 (Box 2)
  - 1950/1951 (Box 2)
  - 1951/1952 (Box 2)
  - 1952/1953 (Box 2)
  - 1953/1954 (Box 2)
  - 1954/1955 (Box 2)
  - 1955/1956 (Box 2)
  - 1956/1957 (Box 2)
  - 1957/1958 (Box 2)
  - 1957/1958-1965/1966, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1966/1967 (Box 2)
  - 1967/1968 (Box 2)
  - 1972/1973 (Box 2)
  - 1973/1974 (Box 2)
  - 1974/1975 (Box 2)
  - 1985/1986 and 1986/1987 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (.8 linear feet) is rich in information regarding the early history of Michigamua and the development of traditions and customs. Other topics well documented are the creation of the Wigwam and the activities of the Old Braves.
  - History and Traditions
    - General, 1923 undated (includes The Great Charter), 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence of William "Billy Bowlegs" Temple with Old Braves regarding Michigamua history, 1933-1935, 1942-1948 (Box 3)
      (includes constitution of The Hot Air Club)
    - Nicknames of Braves (compiled alphabetical lists), 1957 1974 (Box 3)
    - Poems, Songs, and Chants, undated (Box 3)
    - Questionnaires (completed) regarding Michigamua history
      - Tribes of 1902-1919 (Box 3)
      - Tribes of 1920-1941 (Box 3)
    - Ring of Great Warriors, undated (Box 3)
    - Rope Day (Initiation), undated (Box 3)
    - Sachem's Ring, undated (Box 3)
    - Totem Pole, 1958 undated (Box 3)
  - Advisory Board, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Alumni Surveys (used to compile 1967 directory), 1967 (Box 3)
  - Civil Rights Commission, 1976, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Memorials, 1939-1958 (includes preliminary sketches of Fielding Yost Memorial) (Box 3)
  - Michigamua Endowment Fund, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Newsclippings, 1951-1980 (Box 3)
  - Old Braves Council
    - Ann Arbor Council, 1957-1976 (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Chicago, and Lake Erie Councils, 1948-1949, undated (Box 3)
  - Reunions
    - 50th, 1951 (Box 3)
    - 60th, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook Materials
    - 1903-1911 (Box 3)
    - 1921 (Box 5)
    - 1970 (in outsize folder, call no.: UBImul/F41) (Folder 1)
  - Tapping, T. Hawley Tapping, 1940-1947 (correspondence of) (Box 3)
  - Wigwam
    - Building Fund, 1933-1934, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Furnishings and Decorations, 1933, 1940 (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series (.2 linear feet, outsize box, and six outsize folders) is divided into two subseries: Photographs, and Sketches and Drawings.
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries, which includes four outsize folders, dates from 1906 to 1984. Images portray Michigamua members and activities.
    - Event, unidentified probably reunion, undated, 21 strips of color negatives (Box 3)
    - Michigamua Plaza, undated, 1 photographs color Polaroid print (Box 3)
    - Portraits (Box 3)
      ((includes six black and white positive prints of: Henry C. Adams, undated; "Battle Finder" Bartelme, undated; "Slu Foot" Goetz, 1920 W. B. Rea, undated; "Heap Think" Wenley, 1906 one unidentified, undated))
    - Reunion, 1961 (includes totem pole), 2 folders black and white positive prints (Box 3)
    - Rope Day, undated (Box 3)
      (one color positive print)
    - Totem Pole, undated, 1 photographs black and white positive print (Box 3)
    - Tribe Photos
      - Composite Photos
        - Tribes of 1904-1938 (Folder 1)
          (lacking 1914, 1918 1937)
          (located in outsize folder, UBImul/F41)
        - Tribes of 1907 and 1930 (Box 5)
      - Group Photos
        - Tribe of 1902 (Box 5)
        - Tribes of 1910 and 1911, one black and white positive print (Box 3)
        - Tribe of 1976, one black and white positive print (Box 3)
        - Tribe of 1984, photocopy only (Box 3)
        - Tribes, (undated), three black and white positive prints (Box 3)
        - 50th reunion, 1951, 2 copies (Box 3)
      - Rope Day Photos
        - Tribe of, (undated), 2 prints (Box 5)
        - Tribe of ca. 1904 (Box 5)
        - Tribe of 1909 (Box 5)
        - Tribe of 1915 (Box 5)
    - Wigwam, interior, black and white negative (Box 3)
  - Sketches and Drawings
    The Sketches and Drawings subseries consists of one folder of undated sketches of Michigamua logos and an outsize folder of blueprints from 1933 relating to the Wigwam.
    - General (Box 3)
    - Blueprints of Wigwam, 1933 (Folder 1)
    - Poster: Tribe roster, ca. 1906 (Box 5)
- Printed Material
  The Printed Materials series (1 linear foot) is divided into two subseries. The first includes directories, newsletters such as Tower Talk of Michigamua, and programs from the anniversary pow wows and rope days. The second subseries is made up of directories, newsletters, and programs from the alumni groups of Michigamua such as the Old Braves Council, the Michigamua Braves of Fort Detroit, the Lake Erie Wigwam in Cleveland, and various Michigamua classes.
  - Unit Publications
    - Appeals for funding, 1933-1986 (Box 4)
    - Directories
      - 1908-1980, 8 folders (Box 4)
      - Michigamua Sachems, 1902-1934 (Box 4)
    - Histories
      - The Founding of Michigamua, 1902, 1942 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters
      - Tower Talk, 1920-1991, 13 folders (Box 4)
    - Programs
      - Pow Wows
        - Grand, 1904-1922 (Box 4)
        - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary, 1927 (Box 4)
        - Fiftieth Anniversary, 1951 (Box 4)
        - Sixtieth Anniversary, 1961 (Box 4)
        - Sesquicentennial, 1967 (Box 4)
        - Seventy-Fifth, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Rope Day, 1904-1930 (Box 4)
    - Specifications
      - Michigamua Wigwam, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Sub-Units
    - Lake Erie Wigwam in Cleveland
      - Newsletters
        - Smoke Signals, ca. 1950 (Box 4)
        - Tribe of Michigamua, Undated (Box 4)
    - Michigamua Braves of Fort Detroit
      - Newsletters
        - Smoke Signals, ca. 1950 (Box 4)
    - Michigamua Tribe of 1907
      - Totem Pole Legend, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Michigamua Tribe of 1916
      - Newsletters
        - Smoke Talk, 1916 (Box 4)
    - Michigamua Tribe of 1920
      - Directories, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Michigamua Tribe of 1971
      - Directories, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Old Braves Council
      - Newsletters
        - Old Braves Council, 1916-1976 (Box 4)
      - Resolutions
        - Michigamua Endowment Fund, undated (Box 4)